Professor!
Catherine.
Watch your step. OK.
- We have found something beautiful!
l don't believe it. Big, big surprise!
- Yeah? l can hardly wait.
Over here!
Dr. Langford.
- Hello.
What have we here?
Cover stones.
lt's fantastic.
Catherina, come!
What in God's name is that?
- l wish l knew.
. . . there are symbols everywhere.
Names, titles of owners, offerings.
Every other major structure
at the time
was covered in hieroglyphics.
When is the academic community
going to accept that
the pharaohs of the 4th Dynasty
did not build the Great Pyramid?
lnside the pyramid, the most
incredible structure ever erected,
there are no writings whatsoever.
- Dr. Jackson,
you left out that Colonel Vyse
discovered quarrymen's inscriptions
of Khufu's name within the pyramid.
His discovery was a fraud.
Well, l hope you can prove it.
Who do you think built the pyramids?
l don't have any idea who built them.
Men from Atlantis?
Or Martians perhaps?
The point is not who built them,
it is when they were built.
l mean we all know,
new geological evidence
dates the Sphinx back to
a much earlier period. Knowing this,
we ought to re-evaluate everything
we've come to accept about . . .
l've been able to show
a fully developed writing system
appeared in the 1st two dynasties.
Almost as if it was based on
an even earlier prototype.
ls there a lunch or something,
that everybody . . . ?
Dr. Jackson!
- What? Yes?
Someone wants to speak with you.
The Air Force? What is this?
- Could you step over
to the car?
We goin' somewhere?
- You're gonna be fine.
We'll take care of these.
Those your parents?
Foster parents.
What is this all about?
A job.
What kind of a job?
Translation.
Ancient Egyptian hieroglyphics.
lnterested?
l'm gonna go now.
Go where?
You've just been evicted.
Your grants have run out.
Everything you own
is in those two bags.
You want to prove
that your theories are right?
This is your chance.
What's this?
Travel plans.
Mrs. O'Neil?
Come on in.
Mrs. O'Neil, is your husband home?
Yes.
Could we speak with him?
You can try.
Excuse me, Colonel O'Neill,
we're from General West's office.
We're here to inform you
that you've been reactivated.
That guy's a mess.
How'd he get like that? - His kid
accidentally shot himself. - Jesus.
Cleared.
Cold?
Allergies.
Always happens when l travel.
There you go.
Dr. Jackson, Dr. Gary Meyers.
- Hello. - How are you?
What is this place?
- Nuclear missile silo.
Now don't worry, it's been
completely converted. Barbara Shore.
OK, Jackson, welcome to the well.
- Hello.
Where did you find this?
- Giza Plateau, 1928.
l've never seen anything like this.
- Of course you haven't.
No one has.
- There's two lines of hieroglyphics.
The inner track has
the classic figures.
But the outer is like
the cartouche in the center.
We've never found this writing before.
- Those aren't hieroglyphics.
lt might be
some kind of hieratic or cuneiform.
The translation
of the inner track is wrong.
Must have used Budge.
Don't know why anyone would.
What are you doing?
We've used every known technique.
That's funny, ''Gebeh,'' eh?
Yeah.
- Then an adverbial, ''sedjem-en-ef.''
Then ''sealed and . . . buried.''
Excuse me, what are you doing?
lt's not ''coffin.''
lt's ''for all time.''
Who the hell did this?
l . . . l did.
This should be ''A million years
into the sky is Ra, Sun God,
sealed and buried for all time.''
lt's not ''door to heaven,''
it is . . .
''Stargate.''
So why is the military interested
in 5,000 year-old tablets?
My report says ten thousand.
Afternoon, Colonel.
Do l know you? - Colonel Jack O'Neil,
from General West's office.
l'll be taking over from now on.
10,000 is ludicrous. Egyptian culture
didn't even exist until . . .
We know, but radiocarbon tests
are conclusive. - Was there a tomb?
No, but something a lot
more interesting. - Excuse me.
This information
has become classified.
No information
is to be passed on to civilians
without my express permission.
What's going on?
- l'm not sure.
Colonel O'Neil.
You owe me an explanation.
l was told l had complete autonomy.
Plans change.
Why are you here?
Why did they bring you
on this project?
l'm here in case you succeed.
TWO WEEKS LATER
No matches whatsoever with cuneiform
and other pre-dynastic hieroglyphics.
l've exhausted all references
comparing the cartouche symbols
against all known writings
from the period.
Still no similarities.
l'm never gonna get paid.
Can l borrow this?
Orion.
Right here, Daniel.
- Jackson,
this is General West.
- Oh, right, General.
So you think you've solved in 14 days
what they couldn't solve in 2 years?
Any time.
l have some stuff to look at.
lf you'll just pass 'em down.
You'll have to share.
l don't have enough.
Anyway . . .
Here is a picture of the cover stones.
The symbols on the outer track
that you thought were words,
were, in fact, star constellations.
These were placed in an order,
forming a map or address of sorts.
Seven points to outline
a course to a position.
To find the destination within
any three-dimensional space
we need six points
to determine an exact location.
You said you needed seven points.
Well no,
six for the destination.
but to chart a course
you need a point of origin.
Except
there's only six on the cartouche.
The 7th isn't actually
inside the cartouche. lt's just below,
designated by . . .
a little pyramid with . . .
two . . .
funny . . .
neat little guys and a funny line
coming out of the top.
Anyway, uh . . .
He did it.
No.
That symbol isn't on the device.
What device?
Show him.
What is that?
lt's your ''Stargate.''
Come, Jackson.
Monitors up!
- Monitors are up.
Mitch, bring up the details on
the center monitor, please?
l've got details on.
Hold it.
Wait a minute.
You have a, uh . . .
. . . here. Sorry.
Hey, don't!
- Two figures . . .
on either side,
praying beside a pyramid
with the sun directly above it.
He's right.
lt was in front of us the whole time.
General West,
Jackson has identified the 7th symbol.
Go ahead. - Programming
7th symbol into computer.
Chevron 1 is holding.
Chevron 1 in place.
Power output at 23 percent.
Chevron 2 is holding.
Engaged. - Chevron 2 locked in place.
- We're at 35 percent.
Condition red in the gate.
Evacuate all personnel.
Area secure.
Heading back. Seal the door.
This was under the cover stones?
- Yes. My father found it. 1928.
Made out of a mineral
unlike any found on Earth.
Chevron 5 lock in place.
79 percent.
Chevron 6 is holding.
Chevron 6 is locked in place.
This is as far as we've
ever been able to get.
The breakers aren't holding.
Override manually.
Chevron 7 is locked in place.
Send in the probe.
Let's go!
Yes, sir.
Record all information from the gate.
Clear inner silo for approach.
- Everybody outta here. - Let's go!
lt's guiding itself.
Can you believe that?
The beam
has locked itself onto a point
somewhere in the Kaliam galaxy.
lt has mass. lt could be a moon
or a large asteroid.
Where are we on that?
The blue dot.
That's right, Jackson.
lt's on the other side
of the known universe.
We're losing the signal.
This is what the probe sent us.
Freeze and enhance.
You can clearly see
the gate on the other side.
The gates must have functioned
as a doorway between our worlds.
These readings
say it's an atmospheric match.
Pressure, temperature, and . . .
most importantly, oxygen.
These markings are different.
They don't match our gate.
- That's why we may have to abort.
This project is for naught
without a reconnaissance mission.
Once there we would have to
decipher the markings on their gate
and, in essence, dial home,
to bring the team back.
Based on this new information,
l don't see how we can do that.
Well, l could do that.
Are you sure?
Positive.
Your call.
You're on the team.
You understand,
this complicates things.
That's why l wanted you, Jack.
We've opened a door
to a world we know nothing about.
l have something for you.
No, l . . .
- Yes.
l found it with the Stargate
when l was a child.
lt has brought me luck.
You can bring it back to me.
Back-up storage.
Reserve power, on.
We're secure. Clear the area.
- Move it, let's go.
Surveillance and monitoring.
. . . equipment, reserve power . . .
lf anybody has anything to say,
now's the time to say it.
Vector tracking set.
Molecular deconstruction in progress.
Jackson, it's alright.
lt's over. Stay with him.
Keep moving.
lt wears off in a minute.
What a rush!
Prepare to move out.
lt's all here, yeah.
Three teams, let's go.
White team, go!
Clear, no contact.
One-two ratio stable.
- Conditions are similar to inside.
l wanna take a look around.
Kawalsky, Feretti.
Move up there, good.
l knew it.
One - three - three - two.
Report.
Our quarter mile perimeter
is just about complete, sir.
Wrap this up, everybody back inside!
l want you all
back through the Stargate in an hour.
You're coming too,
aren't you, Colonel?
Jackson,
start working on the Stargate.
What's that all about?
- l don't know Feretti.
l'm gonna need more time.
There's bound to be more structures,
or some other traces of civilization.
Not this trip. Just get back in there
and re-establish contact.
lt's not that easy. This is a replica
of the great pyramid of Giza.
We're not gonna find any
hieroglyphics or carved relief.
We need to look around more.
Your job is to re-align the Stargate.
Can you do that or not?
No.
You can't, or you won't?
l can decipher the symbols,
but l need an order of alignment.
The co-ordinates
were on stone tablets back on Earth.
l just need to find
something like that here.
What do you mean ''find it?''
You didn't say anything about that.
- l assumed they would be here.
You assumed?
You're a lying son of a bitch!
You didn't mention finding anything!
Set up a camp down here.
Organize our supplies.
You've got your orders.
This is hot.
We're stuck here.
- Don't be such a doomsayer.
Yeah, give it a rest.
- Yes, please.
lf we don't come back soon,
they'll just turn off the other gate.
lt doesn't work that way.
lf you don't turn it off from here,
we're screwed.
So l'm tellin' you guys,
we're not goin' anywhere.
This is a nice tent.
Oh, we each get a tent. That's nice.
. . . the hell is that?
A thermal blanket, don't need that.
l got everything but sun-block.
Shouldn't you be doing something now?
Like getting us outta here!
Foot powder. Great.
That's cold, man.
Base camp is up, sir.
Where's Jackson?
lt's OK. No, lt's OK.
Good boy!
What do you want?
You want some of this?
l wouldn't feed that thing!
lt's got a harness.
lt's domesticated!
Let go of it!
Do something!
Come on!
Help me!
You OK, Jackson?
Kawalsky.
- You dropped these. - Brown.
Get away from me.
Easy.
All right, Jackson.
You're on.
Me?
You're the linguist.
Try to talk with 'em.
What did you say to him?
- Nothing.
lt's OK.
lt's OK. See?
Quartz, primary element.
l can't make it out . . .
lt sounds familiar,
a bit like Berber.
Or maybe it's Chadic or Omotic.
Thank you.
What's that mean?
l have no idea.
He's inviting us to come.
How can you be so sure?
Because he's
inviting us to go with him.
We were looking for signs of
civilization. We've found it.
To get us back home, this is
our best shot. - He's right.
l took some readings
on what they're mining.
This is the same
material as the Stargate.
Radio base camp.
Tell them to keep it secure,
until we get back. - Yes, sir.
Base camp, come in.
- Feretti, l've got 'em.
Come on.
Could you repeat that, sir?
. . . O'Neil says to secure base camp.
Looks like we could be here a while.
OK, sir.
- Understand? - Yes, sir.
What's the story? - We're not
going back. This is not good.
The eye of Ra.
lt's the Egyptian Sun God.
They think he sent us here.
l wonder why . . .
Ra.
Where they all going?
Come in.
Feretti!
Sir, l can't make this out.
Feretti, say again.
We have to abandon base camp!
Repeat, we have to abandon base camp!
lt's useless. lt won't work in this.
Freeman, let's go!
Everybody back inside!
l'll get the ammo.
Get the battery packs!
We're going back right now.
Wait!
Stay here.
What is it, Colonel?
- Sandstorm. Coming this way.
An excellent reason to shoot everyone.
We'll stay until it's over.
Sorry.
We've gotta get back to the pyramid!
Where the hell'd that come from?
Kawalsky, Brown, do you read?
l don't think we should eat.
They might consider that an insult.
Well, we don't want
to offend them now, do we, Daniel?
Tastes like chicken.
lt's good.
lt tastes . . .
Tastes like chicken.
Good!
You said that was an Egyptian symbol.
- Yeah. The eye of Ra.
Then it might stand to reason that . . .
if they know one Egyptian symbol . . .
Yes.
What the hell's going on?
lt seems like
writing is forbidden to them.
What?
They want me to go with them.
Should l stay? l'll go.
l'll be fine.
OK, that's good.
What is that smell?
l think that's good.
My hands are clean. Thank you.
That was very nice.
l smell much better now.
O Christ, l smell like a yak.
Please, no more.
l'm fine.
l'm clean . . .
l thought
you were one of the other cleaning . . .
No, no, no.
You don't have to do that.
Maybe you should go. OK?
lt's OK. Maybe you should go.
lt's OK. lt's all right.
Let me take care of it.
No, it's me.
Thank you, l'm very happy.
Daniel.
l'm Daniel.
We came . . . uh
This pyramid.
See, we came from . . .
We came from the pyramid.
lt's OK.
Never mind.
The Earth.
You know the symbol?
You've seen the symbol?
Show me.
You show me.
Kawalsky, this is base.
Do you copy?
You're wasting the battery.
Never get anything in this storm.
Wait till it passes. - Yeah, right.
l F it passes.
l was stationed in the Middle East.
l've never seen anything like it.
Yeah, yeah . . .
- l don't understand.
Why don't we just
turn the gate back on ourselves.
How hard can it be?
- Great!
We could turn the thing in the
wrong order and end up in outer space.
Do you have any idea how many
possible combinations there are?
No. How many?
Shut up.
What the hell is goin' on?
Spread out.
lt's OK. lt's just a lighter.
See?
Here!
Yeah, it's pretty fabulous.
You're right. lt's pretty stupid.
No, you keep it.
lt's yours.
No!
lt's dangerous!
What is this place?
l'll be damned.
What?
No signal at all?
- Nothing.
More interference?
No.
They're simply not there.
l can't locate Jackson.
l'm lookin' for Jackson.
He wears this jacket.
He's got long hair that come down . . .
No, no.
He wears glasses, so he can see.
l guess ''dweeb'' doesn't mean anything
to you, does it? Why not?
l'm on Planet X lookin' for a dweeb,
He's got long hair.
lt comes over his eyes.
He wears glasses,
and he sneezes.
Chicken, chicken!
Chicken man. You got it.
You want this?
l thought
you couldn't speak their language.
Huh? Hi . . . scared me.
lt's an ancient Egyptian dialect.
lt's evolved independently.
Once you know the vowels . . .
Just answer my question.
l had to learn how to pronounce it.
lt hasn't been spoken
for more than a thousand years.
This says,
''A traveler from distant stars
escaped from a dying world looking
for a way to extend his own life.
His body decaying and weak,
he couldn't prevent his death.''
Apparently his species
was becoming extinct.
So he traveled or
searched the galaxies,
looking for a way to cheat death.
Look here: He came to a world
rich with life where he
encountered a primitive race.
Humans.
A species which he could
maintain indefinitely.
He realized, within a human body,
he had a chance for a new life.
He found a young boy.
As the frightened villagers ran,
night became day,
curious and without fear,
he walked towards the light.
Ra took him and possessed his body,
like a parasite,
looking for a host.
lnhabiting this human form
he appointed himself ruler.
He used the Stargate to bring
thousands of people here
as workers for the mines.
Just like the one we saw.
This mineral is the building block
of his technology. With it
he can sustain eternal life.
Something happened on Earth . . .
A rebellion,
and the Stargate was buried there.
Fearful of a rebellion here,
Ra outlawed reading and writing.
He didn't want
the people to remember.
Jackson, you better take a look.
That's what we're looking for.
They hoped the gate on Earth
could someday be reopened.
l knew they'd have it
written down someplace.
Wait a minute.
Where's the 7th symbol?
lt must have broken.
lt's gotta be here somewhere . . .
l got it here.
lt's worn off.
l can't make it work without it.
All right, that's it. Kawalsky, Brown.
Come on, Jackson.
What the hell is that?
Here. You might need this.
Look out!
Where are we going?
Why are we going to the Stargate?
l can't make it work.
Shoot at anything that comes down.
- What are you doing? - Just cover me.
What is that?
What are you looking for?
- lt's gone.
Put it down, Jackson.
You have come here to destroy me.
What is that?
lt's a bomb.
That's what you were looking for.
What the hell were you thinking?
What'd you come here for?
Wait! Don't!
No!
No! No!
Colonel, it's me.
You all right?
Where's Jackson?
Sha'uri, what happened here?
Ra punished us.
Why?
What happened to Daniel?
Son, we should not
have helped the strangers.
l was dead?
That is why l chose your race . . .
your bodies, so easy to repair.
You have advanced much . . .
harnessed the power of the atom.
What are you going to do?
You should not have reopened the gate.
Son, l will
send your weapon back to your world,
with a shipment of our mineral,
which will increase your weapon's
destructive power a hundredfold.
Why would you do that?
l created your civilization,
now l will destroy it.
But before
my workers question my authority,
you will prove
that l am their one God,
by killing your companions.
lf l refuse?
Then l will destroy you,
and all who have seen you.
There can be only one Ra!
Sha'uri, Ra has called an assembly.
An execution.
Skaara, Nabeh, l want you to listen.
We can't let this happen.
l want you to know
what Daniel told me,
about where our people came from,
and why
we can no longer live as slaves.
Freeman!
Jackson!
Come on! Kawalsky!
To our victory!
We recovered your weapons.
Here, Colonel.
So, what do you think?
They're not exactly special forces,
but they were eager to join up.
Take these guns away, Lieutenant,
before they hurt themselves.
You heard me. Send 'em all home.
- There's no place for them to go.
We could use their help right now.
- For what?
To do what?
Why don't you just tell 'em?
Why don't you tell 'em about the bomb?
What's he talking about?
My orders were simple.
lf l found any possible danger,
blow up the Stargate.
Well, l found some.
Well, your bomb is his now,
tomorrow he's sending it to Earth,
along with a shipment
of that mineral they mine here.
lt'll cause an explosion 100 times
more powerful than the bomb alone.
l'll intercept it
before he sends it through.
Why wasn't l told of this?
- There was no reason to tell you.
You were all gonna go
right back through with Daniel.
l was gonna stay behind
and blow up the Stargate.
lt's the gate on Earth
that we have to shut down.
You're right. But since
you don't know how to get us back,
we don't have that option, do we?
Where are they?
Answer!
We looked everywhere.
Some kids are helping them.
You accepted that no matter what
happened, you wouldn't be going home?
Don't you have people who care?
Do you have a family?
l had a family.
No one should ever have to
outlive their own child.
l don't wanna die.
Your men and these people here
don't wanna die.
Shame you're in such a hurry to.
How could you let them escape?
l will not accept failure!
Why are you laughing?
- Husbands don't do this work.
Husbands?
Married?
Don't be angry. l didn't tell them.
Tell them what?
That you did not want me.
What are you drawing?
The day of our victory.
Connect the moons . . .
This is the symbol for this planet.
That's it.
The point of origin.
What are you doing?
l've found it!
What?
The 7th symbol.
We're goin' home.
Let's go.
You'll bring disaster
to all of us, son.
Father, we will not live as slaves.
Kasuf!
Take a look at your Gods.
Take a good look.
The caravan is approaching.
Send the bomb down to the Stargate.
What's happening up there?
How you doin'?
Damn! Come on, Feretti!
Come on!
Get that door!
Hey, you OK?
Spread out!
Let's go!
We're dead! - Quit talking like that!
- What're we gonna do? - Cover me.
Cover you?
Kawalsky!
Feretti, help me push this thing over.
Send the bomb to Earth now.
l will send it myself.
What are you doing?
- Completing this mission.
We agreed to dismantle the gate
on the other side. - And you will.
That's your job now. l stay
and make sure this goes off.
You've got seven minutes.
Daniel.
What are you doing?
Jackson!
- Wait for me.
Nabeh!
Got any rounds at all, Feretti?
- All out. - lncoming. - Get down!
Kawalsky, we gotta do something.
Damn.
Stop!
l am no longer amused.
You will die together.
Give my regards
to King Tut, asshole.
How much time do we have left?
- 45 seconds.
He's leaving. Turn it off.
- l can't disarm it. - What?
They've got it rigged.
l got an idea.
l always knew you'd get us back.
- Yeah, right. - Later.
Thanks, Daniel.
You sure you wanna do this?
l'm sure.
You gonna be all right?
l'll be all right.
And you?
Yeah.
Yeah, l think so.
Tell Catherine
it brought me luck.
l will.
l'll be seein' you around,
Dr. Jackson